[Music]
Welcome back to the Real News Network.
We're continuing our series of
interviews on reality asserts itself
with John Keryaku. Thanks for joining us
again. Happy to do it. Now, before we
get going, for those of you that saw the
earlier argument we had about whether
Vice President Cheney would leave the
back door open with for the 9/11
attacks, um, and and you were saying
that I just can't believe one of our
leaders would do that. Can you believe
one of our leaders would lie, come
outright, and start a war that might
have cost a million of Iraqis lives?
Yes. Why that?
because because I think that there's
this horrible belief among many of our
leaders here that the lives of foreign
nationals don't count or aren't worth
American lives. And uh to kill a million
Iraqis, 50,000, 100,000 million, I don't
think they really care. Not Americans.
Not Americans.
Mhm. I mean, look at it this way.
Uh when I was a a young junior CIA
analyst, uh I had weekend duty. And when
you have weekend duty, you review all of
the incoming traffic over the weekend
for every country in the Middle East and
South Asia. And I reported one weekend
that uh two Israelis had been killed in
the West Bank in an attack by a
Palestinian uh farmer. This was news,
right? And after I gave my presentation
on Monday morning and I reported that
these two Israelis had been killed, the
Sri Lanka analyst came up to me and
said, "You know how many Sri Lankans
were killed in the war this weekend?
60." And that's not news because Sri
Lankan lives aren't worth Israeli lives
because Israeli lives are almost
American lives. Almost American. And he
was right. And that stuck with me all
these years. And I think that's the view
of many of our leaders, too. If you're
not an American, your life really isn't
important enough to worry about. This is
the theory of a chosen people. It's
American exceptionalism.
I've always thought this is another I'm
just curious of your
reaction. I I used to run a debate show
in Canada and about a year before the
Iraq war began, Charles Crowutamemer was
a guest on the show as part of a debate
and debating sanctions in Iraq.
and he said something that stuck with
me. I I remembered it after the war
began and then it really hit me what
perhaps the significance of it was. Now,
Crowdamemer, for people that don't know,
is is a conservative pundit, very very
connected in Washington, has access to
the most senior people, particularly in
in a Bush administration, right? Mhm. Um
so a year before the the Iraq war
begins, he says in debating the
sanctions, well we have to do the
sanctions and this and that. But yes, he
says, I agree the sanctions are not very
good. We should have gone in. We should
have finished off the first Gulf War and
got rid of Saddam. Then he says, and
this is the key line, but now it's too
late because he has weapons of mass
destruction a year before. So, it really
it hit me that when when when the
inspectors are saying leading up to the
war that there's no weapons, there no
weapons, that's what they wanted to know
because they needed to know there were
no weapons so that they could invade.
Who's going to invade an Iraq with,
according to Colin Powell, Scud missiles
surrounding Baghdad aimed at Israel with
biological weapons? You're going to
invade under those circumstances. You're
gonna invade where he might have some
kind of nuclear weapon, right? I mean,
what do you think? They they actually
they wanted to know there was nothing.
They were convinced there was nothing
and that's the only way they could
actually launch the invasion. I have a
theory about that and I have no proof of
this, but I was at the CIA. I was
essentially Saddam Hussein's biographer
for four years. I was in uh what used to
be called the office of leadership
analysis and it was my job to do these
long-distance psychological profiles on
on Iraqi
leaders in 19 uh 96. Saddam's son-in-law
uh Hussein Camel al- Majid uh defected
to Jordan. Uh Hussein Camel was Iraq's
minister of industry and military
industrialization. He was the father of
the Iraqi nuclear program. Uh, and he
was he was probably going to be Saddam's
successor. He was married to Saddam's
eldest daughter,
Rugged. So, he and his brother, Saddam
Camel, defected to Jordan in the uh in
the mid '9s and uh they were put up in a
palace by King Hussein.
There were press reports that said that
CIA officers had flown out to Jordan to
debrief Hussein Camel and Saddam Camel.
Saddam Camel was in charge of Saddam's
bodyguard
unit. And that these brothers had given
these CIA officers the kitchen sink, the
crown jewels of the Iraqi uh weapons of
mass destruction programs, biological
96, biological, chemical, and nuclear
weapons. In fact, there was no such
debriefing. Uh Hussein Camel never
wanted to meet with the uh with the CIA.
He had no love of the CIA. He was afraid
that Saddam's son Uday was going to kill
him so that U could become the next
president of
Iraq. So these rumors got started in the
press that Hussein Camel was telling the
Americans where all the weapons of mass
destruction were and that the Americans
would then tell the UN so the UN could
go in and find these weapons.
There was evidence in the late '9s that
the Iraqis began destroying much of
their weapons of mass destruction and I
think it was a result of Hussein Camel's
defection. So that by the time George W.
Bush is elected president there are no
weapons of mass destruction. They're all
long
gone. Now Saddam to save face which is
very very important in Arab culture.
Saddam couldn't go public and say we
have no weapons of mass destruction. He
also couldn't say, "We'll let in any UN
inspectors. You can walk around my
palace and you can walk through our
laboratories." He couldn't say that
because that would make him look
weak. So, he had to say exactly the
opposite, to look tough. But at the same
time, he didn't understand that George
W. Bush needed to look tough, too. He
had a re-election campaign coming up in
2004. So, he had to look like he was
strong and he was going to go to the mat
with Saddam. And so they both misread
each other from 2001 to 2004. There's a
little twist of another interpretation
on
this is is that go back to what you were
saying earlier. They wanted to invade
Iraq for a long time. I always thought
that that the Bush family wanted to
invade Iraq. So maybe Saddam's equation
Saddam's equation is I need to make them
think I have weapons of mass so they
don't invade me. So they don't invade
me. And once they find out, and he's
right, cuz once they find out through
Hans Blicks and they find out through
the inspectors, there's nothing there,
right? That's when they invade. Mhm.
Mhm. I think that's exactly what it
was. It was all predetermined. I'm
convinced of that. I I have a passage in
my book where I I come back from
Pakistan and I'm told that in this new
job that I have, uh, I'm going to have
to be read into certain top secret
compartments. And I asked my boss, who
was one of the associate deputy
directors of the CIA, well, what's the
issue? And he said, I I can't even tell
you what issue we're going to work on
until you go sign the secrecy
agreements. So, I walk upstairs to the
um to the floor that houses the Middle
East uh operations offices and uh
knocked on the door. I said, "I'm here
to sign my secrecy agreements." So, he
has me sign it was six different secrecy
documents. And finally I said, "All
right, what's up?" And he says,
"Well, in March we're going to invade
Iraq. We're going to overthrow Saddam
Hussein, and we're going to open the
world's largest air force base so that
we can move all of our air assets out of
Saudi Arabia and deprive Osama bin Laden
of his ability to say that we're
polluting the land of the two holy
mosques."
And I was so stunned. All I could think
to say was, "But we haven't caught Bin
Laden yet. Why would we overthrow Saddam
Hussein when Bin Laden is still running
around?" And he put up his hands and he
said, "The decision's been made. The
White House has already made the
decision." When is this? This is uh
August of
2002. I learned later that my boss had
been told in March of 2002 that we would
invade Iraq in March of 2003. So the
decision had been made early on in the
Bush presidency. The day after the war
in Iraq began, there were massive
protests around the world. On the
weekend of March 22nd, 23rd,
2003, the the media reported 150,000
protesters in Barcelona, but many people
said it was up to a million. Uh more
than a 100,000, maybe 500,000 in London,
and I heard there closer to 6 or
700,000. in Paris at least 100,000 again
maybe more like half a million 150,000
protesters in German cities and another
40 up to 90,000 in Lisbon 40,000 in burn
20,000 in Greece 250,000 in New York
City at least 250,000 said to be again
closer to half a million um alto
together the the estimates of perhaps as
many as 20 million people protested
against the war you're working
way. Uh, and where are you at the time
of the Iraq war? Uh, at headquarters,
this fact 20 million people came out in
the I think it's the largest protest in
the history of the human species. Does
it get through to you guys? No. No. Uh,
to be perfectly honest with you, I don't
have any memory of those protests at
all. In fact, off camera just a few
seconds ago, you told me this is the
first time you ever heard of it. Yeah,
it's the first time I've ever heard of
it. I'm ashamed to even say that, but
no. Public opinion has absolutely no
bearing whatsoever on what happens
inside the
CIA. None whatsoever.
Do you think it had it also seemed to
have no effect on what happened in terms
of the White House and US foreign policy
either? No, not really. But let me tell
you something very important.
Um, there were a lot of protests inside
the CIA that we were going to get
wrapped up in Iraq. Nobody wanted to go
into Iraq. We were obsessed with trying
to find uh Osama bin Laden. And so uh I
went back to the office after I signed
these secrecy agreements and I
complained to my boss and I said, "Iraq,
really? This is what we need to do right
now? Invade Iraq?" And he said, "Listen,
I agree with you. Everybody agrees this
is a mistake, but this is the policy and
our job is to support the policy. That's
the job of the CIA." And I remember
participating in these these classified
video teleconferences and there were
very clearly defined lines. The groups
that wanted to do this and the groups
that didn't want to do this. I address
this in my book uh on on the pro-war
side clearly and obviously led by the
office of the vice president. Okay. Vice
President Cheney chaired most of these
meetings, these video teleconferences
that we that we did and we did them
almost every morning, but Cheney was
clearly and he chaired them every
morning. Sometimes it would be Addison,
sometimes it would be Scooter Libby, but
usually it was Cheney. Um the Office of
the Secretary of Defense OSD that was
Rumsfeld completely joined at the hip
with Cheney on Iraq. And what what was
the agenda and who's in these meetings?
daily updates, intelligence
briefing, policy discussion, who's doing
what, who's handling what issue, who's
traveling where, this kind of thing. And
this is all in the leadup to the war.
Yes, this is all in the leadup to the
war. So, you have the office of the vice
president, office of the secretary of
defense, and the national security
council pro-war. Isn't that kind of
unusual that the vice president plays
such a role? This was very unusual. It
was very unusual. And on the other side,
on the anti-war side, you had the CIA,
the State Department, and the Joint
Chiefs of Staff. The Joint Chiefs of
Staff wanted no part of this Iraq war.
They said that this was foolhardy. It
was an unnecessary war. It was a war of
choice. I had great a great deal of
respect for the Joint Chiefs. When I
when I watched them argue why we really
shouldn't be involved in this, this
shouldn't be happening. We need to focus
on al-Qaeda and we need to focus on
finding Osama bin Laden. But like I
said, the decision had been made. And
how does And on these conference calls,
you would have ar joint chiefs would be
arguing with Cheney. Oh, yeah. And how
does Cheney respond?
I've issued an order. You're going to
take the order.
And that was it. He's not the
commander-in-chief.
No, but I mean we were all supposed to
just accept the fact that uh that the
commander-in-chief was the one who, you
know, would give the ultimate order that
that he was speaking on behalf of the
commander-in-chief. And was did did the
president ever get directly involved in
any of this kind? You never ever saw the
president involved in any of these video
teleconferences? No. Does anyone ever
stop to question whether Cheny's really
authorized to do all of this?
Well, I mean, you would think that the
president would uh, you know, see it on
the evening news and call him on the
carpet if he didn't want him doing it, I
suppose. Yeah.
Um, so what what in terms of you
personally, you know, your vision of
Americanism, your vision of, you know,
your role and what and who are you
fighting for? What is all this doing to
you? Well, you know, things began to
change for me after September 11th. Iraq
is what really did it for me. I had a
very very close friend, one of my best
friends from high school who recently
passed away. And he was a lieutenant
colonel uh in the Army reserves. And so
he emailed me the day uh after we began
the invasion. And that's when the press
was using the term shock and awe. So my
friend told me in this email that he was
both shocked and awed. And wasn't this
display of American military might so
great to see? And I emailed him back and
I said, "I'm sickened by it. This was a
war of choice. People are going to die
because of this. We didn't have to do
this. In the meantime, we should be
using this money and these
resources, military manpower, resources
to find Osama bin Laden and to bring him
to justice for the crime that he
committed against the American people."
Now, when you say this is a war of
choice, you're saying that America was
not under imminent threat of attack.
Absolutely not. The Iraqis posed no
threat to us. Not even an existential
threat. There there were no weapons of
mass destruction. And even if there
were, the Iraqis had no delivery system.
Now, if this was to protect Israel, I
would posit that Israel can defend
itself.
That that makes this a war of
aggression. Yes, I believed it was a war
of aggression. That makes it according
to the Nermberg trial the war crime. The
supreme war crime. It's a war crime.
It's a war crime. See, but we're the
winners. And the winners are the ones
who write the history books and decide
who gets prosecuted for what.
President Obama, you would think,
certainly someone who said he was
against the war, would have had a
responsibility not just to focus on the
issue of torture, which he didn't. Which
he didn't. But to prosecute Bush Cheney
for a war crime, but what makes you
think that he would even entertain
something like that? I didn't. No, I
didn't. No, I I was never sanguin. But
it's but it's such a violation of
international law. Number one, the war
crime of the war. But it's also a
violation of international law not to
prosecute these war criminals. See, this
is and and the media never says a word
about this. No, the media never says a
word. The media just gets sucked into
the whole propaganda machine and dragged
along. We just decided we didn't like
these people. And so we were going to go
in and kill them. And that's exactly
what
happened. So in the next segment of our
interview with John, we're going to pick
up his story. 2002 he gets posted to
Pakistan becomes the head of
counterterrorism. So please join us for
the continuation of reality asserts
itself on the real news network.
[Music]